<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The memorie of the most worthie and renowmed Bernard Stuart, Lord D'Aubigni renewed VVhereunto are added vvishes presented to the Prince at his creation. By Walter Quin, seruant to his Highnesse.</title>
            <author>Quin, Walter.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20566</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846081</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846081</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10283)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1002:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The memorie of the most worthie and renowmed Bernard Stuart, Lord D'Aubigni renewed VVhereunto are added vvishes presented to the Prince at his creation. By Walter Quin, seruant to his Highnesse.</title>
                  <author>Quin, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p., [2] folded leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslow,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ I² .</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The memory of Bernard L. D'Aubigni.</note>
                  <note>The folded leaves contain anagrams.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aubigny, Béraud Stuart, 1447-1508 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:1"/>
            <p>THE MEMORIE OF THE MOST WORTHIE AND RE<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>NOWMED BERNARD STVART. Lord <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> renewed.</p>
            <p>Whereunto are added</p>
            <p>VViſhes preſented to the Prince at his Creation.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Walter Quin,</hi> Seruant to his Highneſſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dignum laude virum Maſa vetat mori</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Hor. Od.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlow.</hi> 1619.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:2"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He memorable vertues and actions of the renowmed <hi>Bernard Stuart,</hi> Lord <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> recorded in ſundry hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, although but incidently, and in ſeuerall places, haue inuited, yea in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited me by a collection of them, and of what elſe I could learne concerning him by written Records and credible relations of honorable Perſons, to renew his memory. Which I did firſt in <hi>French,</hi> for that from his youth hee hauing ſerued two French Kings, and bin the most worthy &amp; victorious of all the Commanders imployed by them in their warres: yet are his vertues and braue exployts more ſparingly and ſlightly recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>French</hi> Writers, then by thoſe of the <hi>Italian</hi> and <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Nation, againſt which he warred. And now haue I done the ſame in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for that, albeit hee were borne of an illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Familie in one of the Kingdoms of great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and deſerued wel of them both, as it is teſtified by good Records, and by <hi>Leſley</hi> Biſhop of Roſſe, in his Latine hiſtory of <hi>Scotland:</hi> Yet is he ſcarcely remembred in any other publique hiſtory of either of them. But if any that ſhall read his Memoriall writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by me in <hi>French,</hi> find it in ſome points different from this, let him know that it is not in any poynt of hiſtorie, but onely in ſome amplifications: vvhich I haue endeuoured to better in this, beeing my latter labour.</p>
            <p>The reaſon which induced me thus to write, rather in verſe then in proſe, was, becauſe what I could gather beeing not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for a competent relation of his life in proſe, I might with more libertie and congruitie, enlarge the ſame in verſe by di-<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:3"/>
            <head>THE MEMORIE of the moſt worthy and renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med BERNARD STVART Lord D'Aubigni <hi>renewed.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>IF after death to men, whoſe vertues rare</l>
               <l>And worthy actions memorable are,</l>
               <l>Poſteritie immortall honour owe,</l>
               <l>Which from the Muſes powerfull Art doth flow,</l>
               <l>For their reward; and that prouok'd thereby</l>
               <l>Braue minds apace in vertues race may hie</l>
               <l>To honors Goale: ſuch fame is due by right</l>
               <l>To <hi>Bernard,</hi> Lord of <hi>Aubigni,</hi> that bright</l>
               <l>Like to a ſtarre did ſhine in Vertues ſphere</l>
               <l>Among the worthieſt Knights that euer were:</l>
               <l>Who yet hath not receiu'd his honour due</l>
               <l>In proſe or verſe from any of the crue</l>
               <l>Of all thoſe learned Clerks, that did adorne</l>
               <l>That ancient Kingdom, wherein hee was borne,</l>
               <l>Or that, wherein he was free denizon,</l>
               <l>And to whoſe Kings great ſeruice he had done.</l>
               <l>For more then their Records, the hiſtory</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> his memorie,</l>
               <l>(Though onely by the way) doth celebrate:</l>
               <l>Whereas by warres he did exaſperate</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:4"/>
               <l>And much annoy their Princes and their States,</l>
               <l>Againſt the Crowne of <hi>France</hi> aſſociates.</l>
               <l>His vertues and his acts heroicall,</l>
               <l>As alſo ſtrange his fortune may we call;</l>
               <l>Sith he from forreiners among his foes</l>
               <l>Receiu'd hath greater honor, then of thoſe,</l>
               <l>Who him for Countries ſake and his deſerts</l>
               <l>Should honor and extoll with gratefull hearts.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I this neglect abhorring, and inflam'd</l>
               <l>With loue of his tranſcendent worth haue fram'd</l>
               <l>Theſe verſes to renew his memory,</l>
               <l>And leaue a paterne to poſteritie.</l>
               <l>But of his life no Treatiſe hauing found,</l>
               <l>Whereon with methode this diſcourſe to ground,</l>
               <l>Like to th' induſtrious Bee, which here and there,</l>
               <l>From ſundry flowres, that growing any where</l>
               <l>She finds, doth gather Honie leſſe or more,</l>
               <l>Her Hony-combe that ſhe therewith may ſtore:</l>
               <l>So I from ſundry Nations hiſtories.</l>
               <l>Haue of his vertues, warres, and victories,</l>
               <l>Cull'd and compil'd this ſhort Memoriall,</l>
               <l>Not fabulous, nor hyperbolicall,</l>
               <l>Though couch'd in verſe too homely to ſet forth</l>
               <l>A ſubject of ſuch dignity and worth;</l>
               <l>That ſuch a Muſe to grace it would require,</l>
               <l>As the renowmed <hi>Mantuan</hi> did inſpire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In <hi>Scotland</hi> was he borne a younger brother</l>
               <l>To th'ancient Earle of <hi>Lenox,</hi> whom no other</l>
               <l>Of all that Kingdoms braue Nobilitie</l>
               <l>Surmounted in illuſtrious dignitie,</l>
               <l>For that he from the Royall Stemme did ſpring,</l>
               <l>Ennobled with the ſurname of his King.</l>
               <l>This noble Graffe foreſhew'd in ſpring of youth</l>
               <l>What he would proue in ages riper growth.</l>
               <l>He comely was and gracefull out wardly,</l>
               <l>With actiue ſtrength endued, and towardly</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:4"/>
               <l>In wit and diſpoſition: ſo as hee</l>
               <l>Began betimes ſuch as he ought to bee;</l>
               <l>And to enure himſelfe to euery game</l>
               <l>And exerciſe, that beſt his birth became,</l>
               <l>Miſſpending not of time the precious treaſure</l>
               <l>In ſloth, in riot, or vnlawfull pleaſure;</l>
               <l>Wherin we ſee our youths themſelues to wallow:</l>
               <l>And truly had he not begun to follow</l>
               <l>Thus early in his ſpring-time vertues lore,</l>
               <l>In riper yeeres ſuch had not been the ſtore</l>
               <l>And harueſt of his vertue, as it grew.</l>
               <l>For as we ſee a Veſſell that is new</l>
               <l>With any liquor ſeaſon'd to retaine</l>
               <l>Long time the ſmack thereof; ſo is it plaine,</l>
               <l>That both the vertue and the vice alſo</l>
               <l>Of youth, men hardly grown in yeeres forgoe:</l>
               <l>Yea both of them doe rather grow then ceaſe</l>
               <l>In their poſſeſſours, as their yeeres increaſe.</l>
               <l>But more then vertue vice doth on vs ſeaſe</l>
               <l>Becauſe the ſame our fancies beſt doth pleaſe.</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Bernard,</hi> being ſuch by inclination,</l>
               <l>As alſo by his vertuous education</l>
               <l>And practiſe may we call both wiſe and bleſt,</l>
               <l>That had the skill, and will to chuſe the beſt:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like <hi>Hercules,</hi> who being of that age</l>
               <l>Did ſhew himſelfe both vertuous and ſage,</l>
               <l>When as two women in a forked way</l>
               <l>Him met, the one faire ſeeming, gawdy, gay,</l>
               <l>Perfumed, powdred, painted, by her Arts</l>
               <l>To luſt enticing the beholders harts:</l>
               <l>The other ſhamefac'd, modeſt in attire</l>
               <l>And truly faire and louely, yet the fire</l>
               <l>Of luſt abating with an awfull eye.</l>
               <l>The former from the left hand ſhameleſly</l>
               <l>Before her better ſtepping, ſaid to him:</l>
               <l>Braue Youth, if to this woman ſterne and grim</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:5"/>
               <l>Thou care doe giue, and wilt her footſteps tread,</l>
               <l>In a moſt irk ſome way ſhe wil thee lead</l>
               <l>With great turmoile, and dangers manifold</l>
               <l>In Summers parching heat, and Winters cold</l>
               <l>Through many a thorny ſleepe and craggy ground:</l>
               <l>Wherein no pleaſing Mates are to be found,</l>
               <l>But ſauage beaſts, and monſters fell, to whom</l>
               <l>In end a wofull prey thou ſhalt become.</l>
               <l>But if thou wilt reſolue to goe with mee</l>
               <l>In this my way, thou ſhalt be wholly free</l>
               <l>From all ſuch toyle and danger, paſſing ſtill</l>
               <l>Through flowrie fields and medo wes, where at will</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt moſt pleaſant company enioy,</l>
               <l>And all delightfull ſports without annoy:</l>
               <l>Where <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> ioyn'd with <hi>Bacchus</hi> at thy heſt</l>
               <l>Shall entertaine thee as their welcome gueſt.</l>
               <l>Theſe charming words and pleaſing baits ſo wrought,</l>
               <l>As to her bent well-nigh ſhe had him brought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But th'other comely Matron, that did ſtand</l>
               <l>At th'entring of the way on the right hand,</l>
               <l>This ſeeing, ſaid to him: O noble Youth,</l>
               <l>Let not the ſugred words come from the mouth</l>
               <l>Of this deceitfull Strumpet thee incline</l>
               <l>Her ſteppes to follow, and abandon mine.</l>
               <l>Her beautie is but falſe and counterfet,</l>
               <l>Though to the view and ſale ſhe forth it ſet:</l>
               <l>Mine ſee thou maiſt, although to pleaſe thine eyes</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no curious Art, without diſguiſe</l>
               <l>True and vnſtaind to be: which to thy view</l>
               <l>Her inward falſhood, and my truth may ſhew,</l>
               <l>As painfull, dreadfull, dangerous my path,</l>
               <l>Yea and pernicious ſhe traduced hath,</l>
               <l>Hers vaunting to be pleaſant and ſecure,</l>
               <l>And ſuch as might all ioy to thee procure.</l>
               <l>In both ſhe a moſt ſhameleſſe lier is;</l>
               <l>For that my path, though painfull, leades to bliſſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:5"/>
               <l>And glory: yea the paines thereof are ſweet,</l>
               <l>For that with ſolid inward ioyes they meet.</l>
               <l>Whereas her way, though pleaſant ſhe it name,</l>
               <l>Leads to deſtruction, infamy and ſhame;</l>
               <l>The pleaſures thereof being ſuch as beaſts</l>
               <l>Enioy, her ſports of <hi>Venus,</hi> and her feaſts</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Bacchus</hi> being poiſon to the health</l>
               <l>Of mind and body, and the wrack of wealth</l>
               <l>And honor. Both our wayes, &amp; ends (of which</l>
               <l>No mention made was by this guilefull Witch)</l>
               <l>They that doe follow either her or mee,</l>
               <l>Such by experience find at length to bee.</l>
               <l>I therefore for thine honour and auaile</l>
               <l>Wiſh in aduiſing thee I may preuaile.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Voluptuouſnes and Vertue ſo did ſtriue</l>
               <l>Him after them to draw: which did him driue</l>
               <l>Into a great quandary for a while,</l>
               <l>His fancie to her, that would him beguile,</l>
               <l>Inclining, but his reaſon to the other,</l>
               <l>Who ſought his welfare, as a louing Mother.</l>
               <l>But Reaſon ruling Fancie, Vertue won</l>
               <l>The victory: ſo as he ſoone begun</l>
               <l>To tread her path: whereby he did attaine</l>
               <l>To endleſſe bliſſe and glory, vertues gaine.</l>
               <l>Young <hi>Bernard</hi> ſo did Vertues counſell take;</l>
               <l>And Vice with all her pleaſant baits forſake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He had occaſion in his youth to paſſe</l>
               <l>To <hi>France</hi> from <hi>Scotland,</hi> whither cald he was</l>
               <l>By <hi>Iohn</hi> his Vncle: who before his death</l>
               <l>Did by his will to him as heire bequeath</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Aubigni</hi> the Lordſhip, with the reſt</l>
               <l>Of thoſe demaines that he in <hi>France</hi> poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>And which he moſt deſeruedly had won</l>
               <l>By valiant wiſe and faithfull ſeruice done</l>
               <l>To <hi>Charles</hi> then King: who hauing had a proofe</l>
               <l>Thereof much to his honor and behoofe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:6"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a conflict, chiefly in the fight</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wherein many a noble Knight</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Clarence</hi> died, to grace him more,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Armes he had before</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> three Royal Lillies in a Field</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> in his Coat and Shield</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to him a glorious ornament,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Houſe an honor permanent.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Nephew bent to act his part,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> done by acts of Martiall art</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> went about to win,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> did ſo much excell therein,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the valiant'ſt Knights renown'd</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as alſo worthy ſound,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yeeres increaſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and judge, hent both in war and peace</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ployments. Which in peace he had,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> his Maſter with intent to adde</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of friendſhip to the former band</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ancient league, which without breach did ſtand</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> thither to that end</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mbaſſador did him appoint and ſend:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which his Embaſſie hee did approue</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> both thoſe Kings his prudence, faith, and loue.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Great alſo grew in warfare his command</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> When he was choſen Captaine of that Band</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> this own warlike Nation, that contain'd</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hundred men of Armes, and had obtain'd</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat honour firſt of all the Companies,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Which of that kind did ſince in <hi>France</hi> ariſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Whoſe Princes no diſparagement it hold</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be as Captaines of thoſe Bands enrold.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of this charge, and of each high degree</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> honour worthy ſhew'd himſelfe to bee,</l>
               <l>As did by many his braue deeds appeare:</l>
               <l>Whereof much one by right ſhould him endeere</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:6"/>
               <l>To all great <hi>Britain,</hi> and throughout the ſame</l>
               <l>Immortall glory purchaſe to his Name.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which was, that he with warlike power from <hi>France</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did come to <hi>England, Henry</hi> to aduance,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Long thence exil'd, and but in name and ſhew</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Richmonds</hi> Earle: who when he ouerthrew</l>
               <l>And ſlew the crookeback Tyrant in the field,</l>
               <l>Rich Englands ſcepter gloriouſly did wield:</l>
               <l>The helpe of this his Champion wiſe and ſtout</l>
               <l>Both in his paſſage full of dread and doubt,</l>
               <l>And in the battaile hauing happily</l>
               <l>Been ſuch, as much he furthred was thereby.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>It ſeemeth then to haue been Heau'ns intent,</l>
               <l>That he in <hi>Scotland</hi> borne, and by deſcent</l>
               <l>Of Kingly race, ſhould for a <hi>Scottiſh</hi> King</l>
               <l>Sprung from that Royall Stemme, whence he did ſpring,</l>
               <l>Who both great <hi>Britains</hi> Scepters now doth ſway,</l>
               <l>Prepare to this great Monarchy the way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O how both Nations of this famous Ile</l>
               <l>Are by this Vnion bleſt! which doth exile</l>
               <l>From them all diſcord and vnpleaſant iarr's,</l>
               <l>With all the harmes and woes of former warr's,</l>
               <l>Them tying faſt with concords happy bands,</l>
               <l>And giuing them occaſion hearts and hands</l>
               <l>To ioyne in ſeruing both one ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
               <l>And for their mutuall profit to afford</l>
               <l>All fruits of loue and friendſhip th'one to th'other,</l>
               <l>As if they were the children of one Mother</l>
               <l>Ioyn'd by this Vnion: for which thanks they owe</l>
               <l>To him, from whoſe ſupport ſuch helpe did flow</l>
               <l>To Royall <hi>Henry:</hi> who the Roſes twaine</l>
               <l>Made one by wedlock: whence proceeds againe</l>
               <l>This ſecond Vnion more then th'other bleſſ,</l>
               <l>Made by a King ſprung thence, of Kings the beſt,</l>
               <l>Appointed by heau'ns high and bleſt decree</l>
               <l>Sole Monarch of great <hi>Britain</hi> firſt to bee,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:7"/>
               <l>As well by Vertues purchaſe hauing right</l>
               <l>Thereto, as by inheritance: whoſe might</l>
               <l>Is equal'd by his goodnes, and good will</l>
               <l>Is guided by <hi>Minerua's</hi> arts and skill.</l>
               <l>Whoſe Prudence linked is with Pietie,</l>
               <l>With Iuſtice, and vnfain'd ſinceritie;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Iuſtice is by mercy qualified;</l>
               <l>Whoſe courage is by wiſedome modified;</l>
               <l>Whoſe Maieſtie with modeſtie is deckt;</l>
               <l>Whoſe worth is leſſe in ſhew, then in effect,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Phoebus,</hi> whom, the brighter is his light,</l>
               <l>The leſſe we ſee, his rayes ſo dim our ſight.</l>
               <l>And as he doth to all this worldly frame</l>
               <l>Impar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, beames to benefite the ſame:</l>
               <l>So doth our <hi>Phoebus</hi> well with all men deale,</l>
               <l>As an efficient cauſe of publique weale</l>
               <l>To ſubiects, neighbours, and confederates,</l>
               <l>As likewiſe to all other Chriſtian ſtates,</l>
               <l>Sith he by wiſedome mediates their peace,</l>
               <l>And thereby their commerce &amp; wealths increaſe.</l>
               <l>And as he happy in his perſon is,</l>
               <l>So in his iſſue is he bleſtywis;</l>
               <l>As in his Princely Sonne, both of his feature,</l>
               <l>And phiſnomie the liuely pourtraiture,</l>
               <l>As alſo of the beauty of his mind:</l>
               <l>Who to all kind of vertues well inclind</l>
               <l>Such buds of them doth yeeld in ſpring of youth,</l>
               <l>As promiſe vs in ages riper growth</l>
               <l>Of vertues rare and deeds Heroicall</l>
               <l>A fruitfull harueſt: whereby winne he ſhall</l>
               <l>The name and fame of Albions <hi>Charlemaine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When in his Fathers throne he comes to raigne.</l>
               <l>Who in his Daughter faire is bleſt likewiſe</l>
               <l>From all the worthieſt of her ſex the prize</l>
               <l>Of honor winning by her worth: whereby</l>
               <l>She doth procure to her Elector hie</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:7"/>
               <l>Much happineſſe, as by her bringing forth</l>
               <l>Such Princes, as may for their bloud and worth,</l>
               <l>When th'Emperours election ſhall be free,</l>
               <l>As well Elected as Electours be,</l>
               <l>And daughters matches fit for <hi>France's</hi> flowers,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Romes</hi> Eagles ſpred, or Caſtil's ſtately Towers.</l>
               <l>But ceaſe to range thus any more, my Muſe,</l>
               <l>And by thy homely chanting to abuſe</l>
               <l>The prayſes of ſuch ſacred Maieſty;</l>
               <l>Though it to honour duty do thee tye,</l>
               <l>Yea, and the preſent ſubiect thee inuite:</l>
               <l>And (going on where thou didſt leaue) indite</l>
               <l>To me his worthy deedes, whom we may bleſſe</l>
               <l>As inſtrument of ſo great happineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When as King <hi>Henry</hi> crown'd and ſettled was,</l>
               <l>Lord <hi>D'Aubigny</hi> backe into <hi>France</hi> did paſſe:</l>
               <l>Where by the King and his Nobility</l>
               <l>His valour, wiſedome, and felicity</l>
               <l>In his late action was with great applauſe</l>
               <l>Extol'd and magnifi'd: and for that cauſe</l>
               <l>He worthy was eſteem'd of greater charge</l>
               <l>And place; wherein, as in a field more large,</l>
               <l>Or Theater, he might his Martiall skill</l>
               <l>And proweſſe vſe and exerciſe at will.</l>
               <l>Whereof a fit occaſion ſhortly came:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Charles</hi> then King th'eighth being of that name,</l>
               <l>Encourag'd by his heat and ſtrength of youth,</l>
               <l>And by ambition (whoſe enormeous grouth</l>
               <l>Exceedeth in that age) more hardy made,</l>
               <l>Reſolu'd the Realme of <hi>Naples</hi> to inuade:</l>
               <l>Which to the Dukes of <hi>Aniou</hi> appertain'd</l>
               <l>Some ages paſt, but then from them detain'd</l>
               <l>Was by th'vſurping houſe of <hi>Aragon:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Sforza</hi> Duke of <hi>Milain</hi> egging on</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> to this action, him to be therein</l>
               <l>More forward mou'd. But ere he would beginne</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:8"/>
               <l>He knew, that when his gifts he thus did ſow,</l>
               <l>Thence to himſelfe ſuch fruits ſhould after grow</l>
               <l>Of honour, ſeruice, and fidelity,</l>
               <l>As he with great increaſe ſhould gaine thereby.</l>
               <l>And in effect right ſo to paſſe it came:</l>
               <l>For <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> himſelfe did euer frame</l>
               <l>To honour him, and ſerue him faithfully</l>
               <l>In warre and peace with care and induſtry,</l>
               <l>And with vnfained loue and ardent zeale</l>
               <l>Both to his good and to the Publike weale.</l>
               <l>In his <hi>Calabrian</hi> gouernment appear'd</l>
               <l>This to be true, whiles there the helme he ſteer'd:</l>
               <l>Where ſtill to worke his Maſters good he ſought:</l>
               <l>And what he could for publike good he wrought,</l>
               <l>That people ruling with much equity,</l>
               <l>With moderation and with lenity:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>So as when they his goodneſſe tride and prou'd,</l>
               <l>He was by them much honour'd and belou'd,</l>
               <l>Though they were <hi>Demi-Grecians,</hi> and defam'd</l>
               <l>As factious and rebellious, yea and nam'd</l>
               <l>Diuels by a nick-name old, as yet they are.</l>
               <l>Such force haue vertues eminent and rare</l>
               <l>In Rulers, as the ſtubborn'ſt they allure,</l>
               <l>And them to loue and reuerence procure.</l>
               <l>And for his ſake (ſo much they him reſpected)</l>
               <l>They to the French the better were affected:</l>
               <l>Nor any in that Realme ſurmounted them</l>
               <l>In loyalty to the French Diadem.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The power whereof awhile there being great</l>
               <l>Was much diminiſht by the Kings retreat;</l>
               <l>But more by reaſon of his dalliance</l>
               <l>And negligence, wen he return'd to <hi>France.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>King <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> that had a long time houer'd</l>
               <l>And lurk't to ſaue himſelfe, thereby recouer'd</l>
               <l>Both ſtrength and courage, and was hart'ned more</l>
               <l>By new ſupplies, which from the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſhore</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:8"/>
               <l>Came to aſſiſt him vnder the command</l>
               <l>Of that <hi>Conſaluo</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Hernand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To whom as eminent in worth and fame,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> of Great Captaine gaue the name.</l>
               <l>The King his forces hauing with his owne</l>
               <l>Conioyn'd, and thereby the more hardy grown,</l>
               <l>Into <hi>Calabria</hi> paſſeth in all haſte:</l>
               <l>Where th'<hi>Angeuins</hi> poſſeſſions he doth waſte,</l>
               <l>And all ſubuerts that would his paſſage ſtop;</l>
               <l>Like to a Torrent from a mountaines top</l>
               <l>Downe falling after ſtormy ſnowes and raines,</l>
               <l>Which ouer-flowing all the lower plaines,</l>
               <l>Trees, bridges, cottages and countrey townes</l>
               <l>With violence downe beares, ſubuerts and drownes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> whoſe courage like a Rock</l>
               <l>Or Bulwark ſtrong did nothing feare the ſhock</l>
               <l>Of this his furious force, himſelfe prepares</l>
               <l>Him to encounter, yea and ſtoutly dares</l>
               <l>His paſſage finding out by wiſe foreſight,</l>
               <l>To meete him, hie apace, and with him fight.<note place="margin">Guiec. l. <hi>2.</hi> Iou. Hiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>Neere to the walles of <hi>Seminare</hi> he found</l>
               <l>Him, and his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Champion ſo renoun'd,</l>
               <l>With all their army, which did his ſurpaſſe</l>
               <l>In number farre: but ſuch the valour was,</l>
               <l>Which he himſelfe, and all his warlike crue</l>
               <l>Of Frenchmen &amp; North-Britaines then did ſhew, wiſe</l>
               <l>As they defeated quite their enemies:</l>
               <l>Whoſe Leaders, though themſelues both ſtout &amp;</l>
               <l>They ſhew'd, yet to eſcape by flight were faine,</l>
               <l>The King in danger being to be ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Or taken through the falling of his Steed,</l>
               <l>When faithfull <hi>Altauile</hi> in this his need</l>
               <l>His horſe to him, and for him gaue his life.</l>
               <l>Thus our braue Warriour in this warlike ſtrife</l>
               <l>To his immortall honour ouercame</l>
               <l>A King, and a Commander of ſuch fame,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:9"/>
               <l>As was <hi>Conſalue,</hi> whoſe worth and valiant deedes</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Spaines</hi> renown and greatnes were the ſeedes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But fortune of his glorious victory,</l>
               <l>Or rather of ſo great proſperity</l>
               <l>Of the French Nation growing enuious,</l>
               <l>The courſe of his exploits victorious</l>
               <l>Stop't by a ſickneſſe trouble ſome and long,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>3.</hi> Theuet des hom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes illuſtres en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie de Conſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Which on him ſeaſ'd: wherein as ſhe did wrong</l>
               <l>His glory, ſo much woe thereby ſhe wrought</l>
               <l>To the French ſide, which to decay was brought,</l>
               <l>Not hauing Chiefetaines, able to withſtand</l>
               <l>The re-inforc'd aſſaults of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And of <hi>Conſalue,</hi> that did the French aſſaile,</l>
               <l>And euery where againſt them did preuaile.</l>
               <l>The Vice-Roy, Lord <hi>Monpenſier</hi> without doubt</l>
               <l>Was both a noble perſonage and ſtout,</l>
               <l>But not ſo circumſpect and prouident,</l>
               <l>As needefull was, ſuch dangers to preuent.</l>
               <l>Wherewith Lord <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> that then diſeas'd,</l>
               <l>With ſickneſſe lay, was vexed and diſpleas'd,</l>
               <l>As alſo ſeeing that no new ſupply</l>
               <l>Came from the King, who liuing careleſly</l>
               <l>In pleaſure ſuffred by his negligence</l>
               <l>That to be loſt, which with ſo great expence</l>
               <l>Of treaſure, yea with care and toile ſuſtain'd</l>
               <l>Euen by himſelfe he rather bought then gain'd.</l>
               <l>But this his Champion, (although euer true</l>
               <l>And faithfull to him much diſpleas'd he grew</l>
               <l>That his affaires were in ſo euill eſtate)</l>
               <l>Yet ſeeing that with prouidence and fate,</l>
               <l>Which wrought this change, he ſhould but ſtriue in vaine,</l>
               <l>Himſelfe in end to yeeld thereto was faine;</l>
               <l>When of his long diſeaſe not wholy rid</l>
               <l>By true relation vnderſtand he did,</l>
               <l>How that the Lord <hi>Monpenſier,</hi> hauing loſt</l>
               <l>The field, and with the remnant of his Hoſt</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:9"/>
               <l>Beſieged in <hi>Atella,</hi> did agree</l>
               <l>And ſolemnely capitulate that he</l>
               <l>With all his <hi>Freuchmen</hi> ſhould that Land forſake:</l>
               <l>And therefore he not able head to make</l>
               <l>To th'<hi>Aragonian</hi> forces, nor to mend,</l>
               <l>What was by others mar'd, did condeſcend,</l>
               <l>Though much againſt his ſtomack, to be tied</l>
               <l>To Th'articles already ratified.</l>
               <l>And ſeeing that no hope to him was left,</l>
               <l>Since he was wholy of all meanes bereft</l>
               <l>Of doing ſeruice to his King, or good</l>
               <l>To thoſe diſtreſs'd <hi>Naipolitanes,</hi> that ſtood</l>
               <l>Well-minded and affected to him ſtill;</l>
               <l>He vſ'd his beſt endeuours and good will</l>
               <l>To ſaue that remnant of the <hi>French,</hi> that were</l>
               <l>Suruiuing to their woes and dangers there.</l>
               <l>Then as among the firſt he thither paſt,</l>
               <l>So in departing was he of the laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Much was he grac't, when backe to <hi>France</hi> he came,</l>
               <l>Both by the King, and thoſe, to whom by fame</l>
               <l>His vertues rare and eminent were knowne,</l>
               <l>Which by his worthy actions he had ſhowne,</l>
               <l>As Trees do ſhew their goodneſſe by their fruite:</l>
               <l>Which to him chiefly made them attribute</l>
               <l>What victories and honour had beene wonne,</l>
               <l>And whatſoeuer other good was donne</l>
               <l>In <hi>Naples</hi> by the Frenchmen, as the blame</l>
               <l>Of all the loſſes, croſſes, woes, and ſhame</l>
               <l>By them ſuſtain'd to others they imputed.</l>
               <l>Yea by the King he was ſo well reputed,</l>
               <l>As he was like to ſend him back againe,</l>
               <l>That Kingdome loſt by arm's to re-obtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But he ſurpriſed being in his flowre</l>
               <l>And ſtrength of age by death, which doth deuoure</l>
               <l>As well the young and luſty, as the old,</l>
               <l>And is as much with Kings as ſubiects bold;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:10"/>
               <l>To him ſucceeded <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth by name,</l>
               <l>Who willing to enlarge his power and fame,</l>
               <l>Aſſembled a great Army, by the force</l>
               <l>Thereof to driue away vſurping <hi>Sforze</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Milaine,</hi> which as rightfull heire he claim'd.</l>
               <l>And for that Armies are as bodies maim'd</l>
               <l>Without Commanders valiant and expert,</l>
               <l>Three did he chuſe, as men of beſt deſert,</l>
               <l>To leade his Army:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> whereof chiefe in worth</l>
               <l>And place was <hi>D'Aubigni:</hi> who ſetting forth</l>
               <l>Towards <hi>Lombardie,</hi> when thither he arriu'd,</l>
               <l>Th'Vſurper of his chiefeſt townes depriu'd</l>
               <l>By force or compoſition, put to flight</l>
               <l>His Army, and himſelfe bereft of might</l>
               <l>And courage he compel'd likewiſe to flie</l>
               <l>From <hi>Milain:</hi> whither ſoone the King did hie,</l>
               <l>To take poſſeſſion of that goodly ſtate,</l>
               <l>Commanders valiant, wiſe and fortunate</l>
               <l>Reputing them, who thus did him inueſt,</l>
               <l>But this our noble Knight aboue the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereof ſufficient proofe he ſhortly gaue;</l>
               <l>When by this conqueſt he beganne to haue</l>
               <l>Both more deſire, and greater hope, againe</l>
               <l>By Armes the Realme of <hi>Naples</hi> to obtaine.</l>
               <l>But iudging nothing elſe ſo requiſite</l>
               <l>For this his purpoſe, as that oppoſite</l>
               <l>Th'ambitious <hi>Spaniard</hi> to it ſhould not bee,</l>
               <l>The conqueſt of that Land he did agree</l>
               <l>To ſhare with him, who did thereto pretend</l>
               <l>A title, as he did, and in his end</l>
               <l>Of growing greater did with him conſent.</l>
               <l>And knowing well that to the ſame intent</l>
               <l>He was to chuſe for leading of his Hoſt</l>
               <l>A fit Commander, ſuch a one as moſt</l>
               <l>Could further his attempt, of <hi>D'Aubigni</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He made election: who both warily</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:10"/>
               <l>And valiantly with ſpeede did through the Lands</l>
               <l>Of foes, and doubtfull friends conduct his bands;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Romane Columnes</hi> much endammaging,</l>
               <l>That then aſſiſted th'<hi>Arragenian</hi> King.</l>
               <l>Whoſe Army in his paſſage comne to let</l>
               <l>His troupes from paſſing <hi>Gariglian</hi> he met.<note place="margin">Du Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                        <desc>•••…</desc>
                     </gap> au regne de Louis. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>But when to paſſe the Riuer he did thinke,</l>
               <l>To ſet on them, he ſaw his horſemen ſhrinke:</l>
               <l>Whom thus he loudly did rebuke and taunt,</l>
               <l>To egge them on. Yea lately oft did vaunt,</l>
               <l>That you alone without our footemens aid</l>
               <l>Your enemies would daunt: yet now afraid</l>
               <l>Of them you are: which much your honor wrongs.</l>
               <l>O let it not be ſaid, that in your tongues</l>
               <l>Your courage lies, not in your hands or hearts!</l>
               <l>But brauely act of valiant men the parts,</l>
               <l>And ſhew that you can do as well as ſpeake.</l>
               <l>His words them made, wroth with themſelues, to wreake</l>
               <l>Their anger on their Foes; whom furiouſly</l>
               <l>They charg'd, defeated, and compel'd to flie.</l>
               <l>He <hi>Capua</hi> did beſiege, and quickly take.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Auerſe,</hi> and <hi>Nole</hi> durſt not againſt him make</l>
               <l>Reſiſtance, but themſelues did to him yeeld.</l>
               <l>King <hi>Frederik</hi> would neither ſword, nor ſhield</l>
               <l>More vſe againſt him, ſo much terrified</l>
               <l>He was, and by his Proweſſe damnified.</l>
               <l>Wherefore he by experience in the raigne</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Charles</hi> well hauing learned, how humane</l>
               <l>And true he was, ſome ſent to treat with him,</l>
               <l>That found him not in count'nance ſowre or grimme,</l>
               <l>Nor harſh in words, but meeke and mild in both,</l>
               <l>To helpe him willing, and to grieue him loth.</l>
               <l>When they his anſwere back to him did bring,</l>
               <l>It pleas'd him ſo (if ought could pleaſe a King,</l>
               <l>That from a Throne was forced to deſcend)</l>
               <l>As he reſolu'd in vaine not to defend</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:11"/>
               <l>ABout that time King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſaluo</hi> ſent, with Forces to obtaine</l>
               <l>The ſhare to him allotted in that Land:</l>
               <l>Who ſo preuail'd, as none could him withſtand,</l>
               <l>When as with Armes he did the ſame inuade;</l>
               <l>His Conqueſt the more eaſie being made</l>
               <l>By <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> who did ſubdue the King,</l>
               <l>And ſtately <hi>Naples</hi> to ſubiection bring.</l>
               <l>But both thoſe Nations proud and inſolent,</l>
               <l>In humors and conditions different,</l>
               <l>Contending for their bounds began to iarre:</l>
               <l>Whence did ariſe betwixt them open warre.</l>
               <l>Wherein on the <hi>French</hi> party for a while</l>
               <l>The better hauing Fortune ſeem'd to ſmile.</l>
               <l>And as in former times our <hi>D'Aubigni</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More ſtoutly, skilfully, and happily</l>
               <l>Then any other did in warre command:</l>
               <l>So did he at this ſeaſon, when in hand</l>
               <l>He took the third part of the Hoſt to leade</l>
               <l>Into <hi>Calabria</hi> lately conquered</l>
               <l>By Great <hi>Conſaluo;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for he thence did chaſe</l>
               <l>By force the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and in euery place</l>
               <l>Thereof preuaile: wherein auail'd him much</l>
               <l>His reputation in that country ſuch</l>
               <l>For Martiall deedes, and ciuill gouernment,</l>
               <l>When in thoſe parts he had commandement,</l>
               <l>As they againſt the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did rebell,</l>
               <l>And ioyn'd their Armes with his them to expell.</l>
               <l>Yea, ſuch as were the greateſt of them all,</l>
               <l>And of that Kingdomes Peeres the principall,</l>
               <l>Who did his worth and vertues beſt diſcerne,</l>
               <l>Ioyn'd with him: as the Princes of <hi>Salerne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Biſignan,</hi> with th'Erle, to whom <hi>Milet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Did appertaine: whom enuy did not let</l>
               <l>From ſeruing vnder his command in field:</l>
               <l>In ſo great eſtimation him they held,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:11"/>
               <l>And ſo him lou'd: whereof he had a proofe</l>
               <l>Soone after to his honour and behoofe.<note place="margin">Du Hail. auregue de Louis <hi>12.</hi> Iou. in vn. Conſ. l. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>go de Cardon</hi> from <hi>Sicilie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With puiſant Forces comming furiouſly</l>
               <l>Into <hi>Calabria,</hi> therein to annoy</l>
               <l>The <hi>French,</hi> and if he could, them to deſtroy,</l>
               <l>Our worthy Warrior, who with watchfull eye</l>
               <l>Did ſee, yea and foreſee what th'enemy</l>
               <l>Did, or intended, ioyn'd in haſte together</l>
               <l>His Forces, and with greater haſte them thither</l>
               <l>He led, where he to finde his Foes did looke;</l>
               <l>And through vnhanted wayes his iourney tooke</l>
               <l>Of purpoſe, vnawares them to ſurpriſe:</l>
               <l>Which wiſely he effected in ſuch wiſe,</l>
               <l>As vnexpected he did on them ſet.</l>
               <l>Yet ſo their courage did <hi>Don <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>go</hi> whet</l>
               <l>By his couragious deedes, and words, as they</l>
               <l>His deedes did follow and his words obey.</l>
               <l>Which made the combate, many being ſlaine</l>
               <l>On either ſide, ſo doubtfull to remaine,</l>
               <l>As <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> whoſe eye was in all parts,</l>
               <l>Perceiuing that his footemens hands and hearts</l>
               <l>Beganne to faint, and that they did recoyle,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> footemen ſtriuing them to foyle,</l>
               <l>Commanded <hi>Grigni</hi> with his horſemen light</l>
               <l>Thoſe <hi>Spaniards</hi> to aſſaile: which of the fight</l>
               <l>The Fortune chang'd twixt both Infanteries.</l>
               <l>But ſeeing that their hearts did eftfoones riſe</l>
               <l>Encourag'd by their valiant men of Armes,</l>
               <l>With his <hi>North-Britaines</hi> braue, that no alarmes</l>
               <l>Nor Armes could terrifie, he them aſſail'd,</l>
               <l>And breaking them, againſt their Hoſt preuail'd;</l>
               <l>Which vtterly in th'end he put to flight.</l>
               <l>As at this time his skill ioyn'd with his might</l>
               <l>Made him victorious, ſo did it likewiſe</l>
               <l>In many another warlike enterpriſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:12"/>
               <l>Of conflicts, and of taking Townes and Forts:</l>
               <l>Which, ſeeing Story ſhortly them reports</l>
               <l>But as his meaneſt actions, I omit,</l>
               <l>As acts of greater fame to match vnfit.</l>
               <l>But after this his famous victory</l>
               <l>Her fickleneſſe and mutability</l>
               <l>Did Fortune ſhew: for full of fraud and guile</l>
               <l>Shee on the <hi>Spaniards</hi> now beganne to ſinile,</l>
               <l>But on the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> ſpitefully to frowne,</l>
               <l>And, as ſhe rais'd them vp, to caſt them downe.</l>
               <l>He being chiefe Vpholder of that ſide,</l>
               <l>To which this miſaduenture did betide</l>
               <l>Through Fortunes alteration, did partake</l>
               <l>With them therein: yet could not that him make</l>
               <l>Faint-hearted: yea, in this to his behoofe</l>
               <l>Did Fortunes frowning turne, that for a proofe</l>
               <l>It ſeru'd, the more his Vertue to refine,</l>
               <l>And for a Foile the more to make it ſhine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For truly courage in aduerſity</l>
               <l>Appearing greater Magnanimity</l>
               <l>And worth in th'owner ſhewes, then when it is</l>
               <l>Accompanied with Fortunes ſeeming bliſſe:</l>
               <l>As Pilots do in ſtormes their Art and skill</l>
               <l>Farre better ſhew, then hauing winde at wil.</l>
               <l>Some in renowne of valiancy do flouriſh,</l>
               <l>Whiles Fortune with her fauors doth them cherriſh,</l>
               <l>Who, if ſhe frowne on them, will play the parts</l>
               <l>Of men deiected and depriu'd of hearts.</l>
               <l>And if it chance (which ſeldome chance we ſee)</l>
               <l>That he, who valiant is, ſtill happy be</l>
               <l>In his attempts: yet, in his good ſucceſſe</l>
               <l>Her ſhare and portion Fortune clayming, leſſe</l>
               <l>Appeares his courage, then if he thereby</l>
               <l>Should Fortune daunt and vanquiſh manfully.</l>
               <l>For, though <hi>Timoleon</hi> ſo much fauour'd were</l>
               <l>By her, as euermore, and euery where</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:12"/>
               <l>He had ſucceſſe, ſo as the ſame to ſhew,</l>
               <l>A Painter him with nets Townes taking drew:</l>
               <l>Yet was he not therefore ſo much eſteem'd,</l>
               <l>As many Warriours not ſo happy deem'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O how I much admire that worthy King,</l>
               <l>Renowned <hi>Bruce,</hi> whom Fortune, enuying</l>
               <l>His glory, more then once in warres did croſſe,</l>
               <l>And forc't him to retire with griefe and loſſe!</l>
               <l>Yet could ſhe neuer force him to forſake</l>
               <l>His braue deſſignes, nor him faint-hearted make,</l>
               <l>Who did from all occaſions great and ſmall</l>
               <l>Draw motiues, to ſtirre vp himſelfe withall.</l>
               <l>For when he once a Spider weauing view'd,</l>
               <l>That oftentimes her broken Web renew'd,</l>
               <l>Till ſhe had weau'd it wholy; then ſhall I,</l>
               <l>Said he, demeane my ſelfe leſſe conſtantly,</l>
               <l>In that which doth concerne my countryes good,</l>
               <l>And mine own right by Fortunes ſpite withſtood,</l>
               <l>Then doth this vermine when it thus doth weaue?</l>
               <l>No, no: for all th'affronts, that I receaue</l>
               <l>From Fortune, to her ſhall not make me yeeld,</l>
               <l>Nor as a Coward quite my ſword or ſhield,</l>
               <l>Till I my foes ſhall vanquiſh, and her might,</l>
               <l>And winne the Kingdome that is mine by right.</l>
               <l>So ſpake, ſo did he; and though his attempt</l>
               <l>From many dangers great were not exempt,</l>
               <l>Yet he by valiant conſtancy therein</l>
               <l>Did Fortune vanquiſh, and a Kingdome winne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Lord <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> who to his Royall race</l>
               <l>Was neere in bloud, and whom the heau'ns did grace,</l>
               <l>As they did him, with Magnanimity</l>
               <l>In ouercomming Fortunes enmity,</l>
               <l>Preceyuing, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> did beginne</l>
               <l>Vpon the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> dayly ground to winne,</l>
               <l>Their ſtrength decreaſing, and no new ſupply</l>
               <l>From <hi>France</hi> arriuing them to fortifie,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:13"/>
               <l>Their Paſſions, them thus gently taxed hee.</l>
               <l>Deare kinſmen, I am greeu'd thus you to ſee</l>
               <l>Deiected and disheartned, who ſhould proue</l>
               <l>Of Valiant courage, Paternes fit to moue</l>
               <l>All Noble Youths the ſame to imitate;</l>
               <l>Not ſuffering any chance infortunate</l>
               <l>Your manly courage womanly to make,</l>
               <l>Or thus your ſelues, like women, to betake</l>
               <l>To teares and wailing. What? thus will ye wrong</l>
               <l>That ancient Royall Stocke, whence you are ſprung,</l>
               <l>As from it to degenerate ſo much,</l>
               <l>Or wrong your Countries Honor; which is ſuch,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Britaines</hi> haue th' old <hi>Romanes</hi> property</l>
               <l>And praiſe, to act and ſuffer valiantly?</l>
               <l>Let courage then ſuch tenderneſſe remoue</l>
               <l>From you, and (as it much doth you behoue)</l>
               <l>Let reaſon, without too much griefe or feare,</l>
               <l>All Fortunes changes make you ſtoutly beare;</l>
               <l>Eſpecially in Warre, wherein more rife</l>
               <l>They are, then in the remnant of our life:</l>
               <l>Since by experience oft it hath beene ſeene,</l>
               <l>That they which haue one day victorious beene,</l>
               <l>Another day, yea and perhaps the ſame</l>
               <l>Haue loſt the field, ſuch is <hi>Bellonas</hi> game.</l>
               <l>And therefore as on Fortune to rely</l>
               <l>Too much yee ought not; ſo you are to fly</l>
               <l>Of her, or of your ſelues a baſe diſtruſt:</l>
               <l>Yea brauely ſtriue to vanquiſh her yee muſt,</l>
               <l>And make her by your valiancy renew'd</l>
               <l>As friendly to you, as ſhe now is ſhrewd.</l>
               <l>Thus both in deeds and words he made appeare</l>
               <l>His Courage and his Vertue bright and cleare,</l>
               <l>As well when Fortunes ſtormes did him aſſaile,</l>
               <l>As when her fauours moſt did him auaile.</l>
               <l>He priſoner in <hi>Naples</hi> did remaine,</l>
               <l>Till, when the warre was ceaſ'd, to France againe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:13"/>
               <l>He was to goe with other men of worth.<note place="margin">Iou. in vit. Conſ. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note>
               </l>
               <l>To them <hi>Conſaluo</hi> at their ſetting forth</l>
               <l>Did offer horſes with much courteſie</l>
               <l>For their returne: for which our <hi>D'Aubigni</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Him thanking, thus did anſwere him: My Lord,</l>
               <l>Since that your bounty doth to vs afford</l>
               <l>To beare vs horſes, we would haue them ſtrong,</l>
               <l>That they to France may carry vs along,</l>
               <l>And hither backe. <hi>Conſaluo</hi> what he ſaid</l>
               <l>Well vnderſtanding, thus him ſtraight repaid:</l>
               <l>Returne, when it ſhall pleaſe you, Lords, for I</l>
               <l>Towards you will vſe like liberality,</l>
               <l>Both horſes, and my Paſport giuing you</l>
               <l>As willingly, as I you giue them now.</l>
               <l>Theſe words their quickneſſe in conceit did ſhew,</l>
               <l>And Noble mindes, ſuch as are found in few.</l>
               <l>Yet ſhew they moſt his magnanimity,</l>
               <l>Who thus could ieſt in his aduerſity.</l>
               <l>If we the warriours of their time compare</l>
               <l>With them, among them all they peereleſſe are.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such by two famous King's eſteem'd they were,</l>
               <l>Soone after meeting at <hi>Sauona:</hi> where</l>
               <l>King <hi>Lewis</hi> of France inuiting to a feaſt</l>
               <l>The King of Spaine, <hi>Conſaluo</hi> as a gueſt</l>
               <l>With him inuited, and moſt courteouſly</l>
               <l>Him vſing, did extoll and magnifie</l>
               <l>The worthineſſe that did in him abound,</l>
               <l>His Martiall deedes, and victories renow'nd.</l>
               <l>All which his iealous King did little pleaſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lewis,</hi> peraduenture knowing his diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Thus to increaſe it, did <hi>Conſaluo</hi> grace.</l>
               <l>King <hi>Ferdinand</hi> behind hand in this caſe</l>
               <l>Was not with <hi>Lewis:</hi> but as <hi>Lewis</hi> of his traine</l>
               <l>The worthieſt Warriour choſe; ſo hee againe</l>
               <l>Deſirous choiſe of ſuch a gueſt to make,<note place="margin">Mariana hiſt, Hiſp. l. 29.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.9.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Among the French our <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> did take</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:14"/>
               <l>For ſuch, and in like ſort him entertain'd.</l>
               <l>To whom this honour high his merits gain'd,</l>
               <l>Though he a <hi>Britain</hi> were, and in degree</l>
               <l>To Princes Dukes, and Peeres that chanc'd to bee</l>
               <l>There at that time inferiour farre, ſo bright</l>
               <l>Did vertue ſhine in this renowmed Knight.</l>
               <l>The fauour of theſe Monarchs to theſe twaine</l>
               <l>Was of their matchleſſe worth a witneſſe plaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if them both we doe compare together</l>
               <l>(Which fitly may be done) both th'one and th'other</l>
               <l>Were younger brethren to two Noble Lords;</l>
               <l>To whom in what inheritance affords</l>
               <l>Inferiour being more they were then mates</l>
               <l>To them by their own purchaſe of eſtates,</l>
               <l>And honour made by their induſtrious care,</l>
               <l>And by their vertues eminent and rare.</l>
               <l>For induſtrie, which both did help to raiſe,</l>
               <l>Lord <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> deſerues the greater praiſe:</l>
               <l>Sith he no <hi>Frenchman</hi> beeing, could in <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By induſtrie himſelfe ſo much aduance:</l>
               <l>Where th'other great in his owne Countrey grew,</l>
               <l>Grac'd by a Queene,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abel Queene of Spayne.</note> that him to action drew</l>
               <l>In vertue both excell'd, yet different were</l>
               <l>In that our <hi>Bernards</hi> vertue was ſincere;</l>
               <l>Where th'others hauing ſtill a gliſtering ſhew,</l>
               <l>Sometimes more artificiall was then true.</l>
               <l>Both th'one and th'other of a noble mind,</l>
               <l>And truly generous to haue beene we find.</l>
               <l>Yet when on both malignant Fortune fround,</l>
               <l>More courage did in <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> abound.</l>
               <l>With Prudence both were plentifully ſtor'd:</l>
               <l>Yet tax'd and branded is the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Lord</l>
               <l>For craft and breach of faith in hiſtories;</l>
               <l>Which th'other name no leſſe vpright then wiſe.</l>
               <l>For valiancy, that like in both w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> found,</l>
               <l>Among the valiant'ſt both may be renown'd.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:14"/>
               <l>In Martiall skill they may be paralel'd,</l>
               <l>And iuſtly for great Captaines both be held:</l>
               <l>Although to win that name, th'one Fortunes ayd</l>
               <l>Had more then th'other: for <hi>Conſaluo</hi> ſway'd</l>
               <l>And rul'd, as beſt him pleas'd, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide:</l>
               <l>Where <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> ſo could not rule and guide</l>
               <l>The <hi>French,</hi> another being then <hi>Vice-roy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet did he ſo the power he had imploy,</l>
               <l>As in both warres made for that Kingdome, none</l>
               <l>Of all that led the <hi>French,</hi> but he alone,</l>
               <l>Wonne any great and famous victory,</l>
               <l>As witneſſeth that Ages hiſtorie.</l>
               <l>Whereby this truth is alſo teſtified,</l>
               <l>That not <hi>Conſaluo,</hi> ſo much magnified</l>
               <l>So oft victorious was in field as hee.</l>
               <l>For beſides leſſer conflicts, battailes three</l>
               <l>He wonne, the firſt of them at <hi>Seminare;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wherein <hi>Conſalue</hi> had of the loſſe his ſhare</l>
               <l>With <hi>Ferdinand</hi> then King; at <hi>Gariglian</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The next againſt King <hi>Fredericks</hi> hoſt he wanne;</l>
               <l>The third, neere to <hi>Terine:</hi> whereas but twice</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conſalue</hi> in battaile rang'd (although the price</l>
               <l>Thereof was all that Kingdome) vanquiſhed</l>
               <l>The <hi>French</hi> by <hi>Nemours,</hi> and <hi>Gonzaga</hi> led.<note place="margin">Iou. in vit Conſ. lib. 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>This of our Warriour <hi>Iovius</hi> more doth tell,</l>
               <l>That after the miſchance, which him befell</l>
               <l>But once in warre, of Fortune he complain'd,</l>
               <l>That him, who had twelue victories obtain'd,</l>
               <l>Since he in <hi>Britain,</hi> and in <hi>France</hi> betooke</l>
               <l>Himſelfe to warre, ſhe thus in end forſooke.</l>
               <l>Whereby appeareth how this noble Knight</l>
               <l>By ſilence is defrauded of his right:</l>
               <l>As alſo we may well thereby obſerue,</l>
               <l>That oftentimes ſuch men as beſt deſerue,</l>
               <l>Are leſſe then men of leſſe deſert reſpected,</l>
               <l>And in their fame, as other wiſe neglected.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:15"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But this to him the rather hath arriu'd,</l>
               <l>For that almoſt continually he liu'd</l>
               <l>In forrein Lands, and all his famous deeds</l>
               <l>In them atchiev'd: where ſeldome any heed's</l>
               <l>A Strangers worthy Acts, or takes the paines</l>
               <l>Them to record, but for reward and games:</l>
               <l>For which reſpect <hi>Conſalue</hi> ſo much renown'd,</l>
               <l>Beſides the Spaniards that his praiſes ſound,</l>
               <l>Hath had the learned <hi>Iouius</hi> him to praiſe:</l>
               <l>Who by the way, the more his worth to raiſe,</l>
               <l>In part the worth of <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> record's,</l>
               <l>As of his chiefe Opponent: which affords</l>
               <l>Occaſion thus to paragon together</l>
               <l>Theſe two renowmed warriours: whereof either</l>
               <l>Did th'others worth eſteeme and magnifie,</l>
               <l>Though different in this, that <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As beſt it with his Maſters pleaſure ſtood,</l>
               <l>Or moſt behoofull was for publike good,</l>
               <l>Alone, or ioyn'd with others in the field</l>
               <l>Did gouerne, or the place to others yeeld.</l>
               <l>Whereas, ſuch was the Spaniards hauty heart,</l>
               <l>As euermore he a Commanders part</l>
               <l>Did ſtriue to act:<note place="margin">Iou. in vita Conſ. lib. 3.</note> for which he well compar'd</l>
               <l>Was to a Carracke huge, built and prepar'd,</l>
               <l>Rigg'd, trimm'd, and furniſh'd with exceſſiue charge,</l>
               <l>Which well may ride aflote, or ſaile at large</l>
               <l>In the deepe Ocean, but cannot abide</l>
               <l>A ſhallow Hav'n, or neere the ſhore to ride.</l>
               <l>Whereas our Brittiſh Lord compar'd may be</l>
               <l>To one of thoſe Ships Royall, which we ſee</l>
               <l>Neere Chattam, fit to ſaile into the Maine</l>
               <l>To ſerue her King, and to returne againe</l>
               <l>Into her Hav'n, or, when a boyſtrous blaſt</l>
               <l>At Sea doth take her, neere the ſhore to caſt</l>
               <l>Her Anchor, riding there from ſtormes ſecure.</l>
               <l>So euermore did he himſelfe enure</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:15"/>
               <l>Both to his duty and his fortune ſtill,</l>
               <l>Though free from baſeneſſe to conform his will.</l>
               <l>By all that hath beene hitherto recorded</l>
               <l>Of him, to him this praiſe may be afforded</l>
               <l>Deſeruedly, that many did him giue,</l>
               <l>Who chanced in his company to liue;</l>
               <l>To wit, that among Warriours none they knew,</l>
               <l>That did in Warre more skill and valour ſhew;</l>
               <l>No Councellor or Gouernour in Peace</l>
               <l>More wiſe; and in proſperities increaſe</l>
               <l>None more humane and gentle; as likewiſe</l>
               <l>None in aduerſity that play'd his prize</l>
               <l>More brauely againſt foes, and Fortunes ſpite:</l>
               <l>So as this praiſe doth iuſtly me inuite,</l>
               <l>Together with his other Merits rare,</l>
               <l>With great <hi>Conſalue</hi> in worth him to compare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But that in matching them I may forbeare</l>
               <l>To be too tedious, after that they were</l>
               <l>So graced by the Kings of France and Spaine,</l>
               <l>Their fortune, like to <hi>Cynthia</hi> in her waine,</l>
               <l>Decreaſed, ſo as neyther of them was</l>
               <l>In warfare more imployed: which came to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Not for that they, as men with action cloy'd,</l>
               <l>Were grown vnwilling ſo to be imploy'd,</l>
               <l>But through their <hi>Masters</hi> great ingratitude,</l>
               <l>Which them from ſuch employment did exclude;</l>
               <l>Were it for that ſo great were their deſerts</l>
               <l>And ſeruice, as their Maſters narrow hearts</l>
               <l>Did them, as too much owing to them, lothe,</l>
               <l>Or that with them by whiſpering ſlanders wroth</l>
               <l>They were become, or did their faith diſtruſt.</l>
               <l>But whatſoeuer was the cauſe, ſo thruſt</l>
               <l>They out of fauour were. But the diſpleaſure</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> not hauing end nor meaſure</l>
               <l>Againſt <hi>Conſaluo, Lewis</hi> did ſoone relent,</l>
               <l>And reconcil'd to <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> he ment</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:16"/>
               <l>Him in ſome famous action to employ.</l>
               <l>But ſicklineſſe did him ſo much annoy,</l>
               <l>As he therefore was counſel'd to repaire</l>
               <l>To <hi>Scotland,</hi> that by that his natiue ayre</l>
               <l>He might his health recouer: which aduice,</l>
               <l>And Countreys loue did him thereto entice.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He thither ward through <hi>England</hi> tooke his way:</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Henry</hi> th'eighth by name, that then did ſway</l>
               <l>The Seepter of this Land, remembring well,</l>
               <l>What furtherance he heard his Father tell</l>
               <l>This Lord him gaue, when to the Crowne he came,</l>
               <l>And hauing vnderſtood by publique fame</l>
               <l>Much of his worthy deeds, him to preſent</l>
               <l>His dutie to him comne with great content</l>
               <l>Did graciouſly receiue and entertaine,</l>
               <l>Inuiting him in <hi>England</hi> to remaine</l>
               <l>By bounteous offers: but with reuerence</l>
               <l>He thanking that great Monarch, homeward hence</l>
               <l>Departed: where with honour and applauſe</l>
               <l>The King and all eſtates, not without cauſe</l>
               <l>His worth eſteeming much, did him receaue.</l>
               <l>There ſhortly after death did them bereaue</l>
               <l>Of him their rare and precious ornament.</l>
               <l>For which their loſſe in him they did lament:</l>
               <l>As did his friends in <hi>France,</hi> and euery where,</l>
               <l>Enamour'd with his vertue, as it were</l>
               <l>A Loadſtone, drawing to him many hearts:</l>
               <l>So as in many Ages for deſerts</l>
               <l>None was belou'd and honour'd more, then he</l>
               <l>In ſundry Lands by men of each degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea death, which doth the greateſt, whiles they liue</l>
               <l>Enioying loue and honour, oft depriue</l>
               <l>Of both, yet could not him bereaue of either,</l>
               <l>As well we may by one example gather.</l>
               <l>Which is, that the Commanders of the Hoſt</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Frauncis, France's</hi> Monarch, in the Coaſt</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:16"/>
               <l>Of <hi>Piemont,</hi> hauing taken by ſurpriſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Columne</hi> a Chiefetaine other times ſo wiſe,</l>
               <l>That he like <hi>Fabius</hi> was his Countries ſhield;</l>
               <l>As priſoner himſelfe he would not yeeld</l>
               <l>To <hi>La Paliſſe,</hi> or <hi>Bayard,</hi> though renown'd</l>
               <l>Aboue the reſt they were: but hauing found</l>
               <l>That <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> was of the chiefeſt one,</l>
               <l>He did his perſon yeeld to him alone,</l>
               <l>As Neuew to our famous <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whom he had in the warres of <hi>Italy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Well known, and highly for his worth eſteem'd,</l>
               <l>So as his Neuew for his ſake he deem'd</l>
               <l>Moſt worthy thus by him to be affected,</l>
               <l>And more then all the reſt to be reſpected.</l>
               <l>To <hi>Bernard</hi> ſuch was his reſpect and loue,</l>
               <l>As death from him could not the ſame remoue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His worth, that did allure this worthy Knight</l>
               <l>Thus him to loue, and honor doth by right</l>
               <l>Stirre vp my homely Muſe thus to renew</l>
               <l>His memory with prayſes to him dew</l>
               <l>Among our <hi>Britaines:</hi> to whom he their owne</l>
               <l>Should be as well, as among ſtrangers knowne,</l>
               <l>Yea better, ſince to him they partly owe</l>
               <l>Both th'Vnions (whence their happineſſe doth flow)</l>
               <l>Of both the Roſes, and the Kingdomes twaine,</l>
               <l>With double thanks for this their double gaine.</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertuous deeds the rather I ſet forth,</l>
               <l>That worthy mindes may imitate his Worth,</l>
               <l>And worthily aſpire to his renowne:</l>
               <l>Which length of time ſhall not in <hi>Lethe</hi> drowne,</l>
               <l>Whiles of his Worth and Name, the Memory</l>
               <l>Shall be preſeru'd by many a Hiſtory</l>
               <l>In <hi>Romane, Tuſcaue, French</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſcroules,</l>
               <l>As alſo kept in theſe my <hi>Engliſh</hi> Roules.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:17"/>
            <head>Of his laſt retiring to Corſtorfin.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LInternum,</hi> though obſcure, the place became</l>
               <l>Of famous <hi>Scipio's</hi> laſt abode, when <hi>Spaine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Carthage</hi> hauing conquer'd, with diſdaine</l>
               <l>Vngratefull <hi>Rome</hi> he loth'd, and left the ſame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corſtorfin</hi> as obſcure in ſhew or name</l>
               <l>Did noble <hi>Bernard</hi> for her gueſt retaine,</l>
               <l>From thankeleſſe <hi>France</hi> when he came home againe,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Scipio</hi> like in Fortune as in fame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Linternum,</hi> whileſt her venerable gueſt</l>
               <l>Did her inhabite, greater Worth poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>Then great and wealthy <hi>Rome</hi> in all her treaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Corstorfin</hi> alſo may be ſaid as well,</l>
               <l>Whiles worthy <hi>Bernard</hi> deign'd therein to dwell,</l>
               <l>Of Worth to haue poſſeſt, as great a meaſure.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Of his buriall in the ſame place.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>BRaue <hi>Bernard,</hi> of a Noble Linage borne</l>
               <l>In <hi>Scotland,</hi> whom ſuch Vertues did adorne,</l>
               <l>As did him more ennoble, and in <hi>France</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deſeruedly to honour high aduance;</l>
               <l>Who <hi>Englands</hi> parted Roſes, and with them</l>
               <l>The <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Thiſtle in their Royall Stemme</l>
               <l>Help'd to vnite; who of a Ruler wiſe</l>
               <l>And valiant Warriour well deſeru'd the prize</l>
               <l>In <hi>Italy,</hi> chiefe Theater of his Worth</l>
               <l>And Victories; whoſe Fame from <hi>South</hi> to <hi>North,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt</hi> did through all <hi>Europe</hi> flye,</l>
               <l>Interr'd doth in obſcure <hi>Corſtorfin</hi> lie.</l>
               <l>But I miſtake: his better part is paſt</l>
               <l>To Heau'n, on earth his fame ſhall euer laſt.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Of the Lords of</hi> Aubigni, <hi>deſcended</hi> from the moſt noble houſe of <hi>Lenox.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>AMong the faireſt Branches that haue ſprouted</l>
               <l>From the Illuſtrious Stocke of <hi>Lenox,</hi> three</l>
               <l>Came in ſucceſſiue order Lords to be</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Aubigni,</hi> like <hi>Mars</hi> in Armes redoubted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The firſt was <hi>Iohn,</hi> whom for his ſeruice loyall,</l>
               <l>And valiant deedes King <hi>Charles</hi> did ſo regard,</l>
               <l>As he with Princely gifts did him reward,</l>
               <l>And to his Scutcheon adde his Lillies Royall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The next was <hi>Bernard,</hi> who ſuch honour gained</l>
               <l>Both by his valiant Acts and Vertues rare,</l>
               <l>As iuſtly we may him with them compare,</l>
               <l>That haue by Worth to Honors height attained.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The third was <hi>Robert</hi> ſo for valour praiſed</l>
               <l>In many a fight, but chiefely in the field</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Marignan,</hi> that Sunne and Moone beheld,</l>
               <l>As to be <hi>France's</hi> Martiall he was raiſed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In calmer times their Heyres occaſion wanted,</l>
               <l>Not valiant hearts, their worth in Armes to ſhew:</l>
               <l>And now their worthy Of-ſpring doth renew</l>
               <l>Their honour in great <hi>Britaine,</hi> there tranſplanted:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Where they in happy manner grow and flouriſh,</l>
               <l>But chiefely he, who ſhines in Worth and place</l>
               <l>Among her Peeres, and whome our Soueraign's Grace</l>
               <l>Deſeruedly doth ſo aduance and cheriſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe goodly branches, whom their Worth commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth,</l>
               <l>From Stemme haue ſprouted of that Royall Tree,</l>
               <l>Which doth from ſtormes with ſheltring ſhadow free</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Britaine,</hi> and in height to Heau'n aſcendeth.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:18"/>
            <head>A ſhort Collection of the moſt notable places of Hiſtories quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>in this Memoriall.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>Haue thought it meete, the better to ſhew how this Memoriall agreeth with Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall truth, to adde thereunto the moſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table places of Hiſtories quoted in the Margent, without altering the ſeuce of the Authors, yea, or their words, but onely in that they are tranſlated, and in the abridgement of ſome narrations, wherein other mens acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are interlaced. To the ſaid paſſages I haue added nothing but the connexion, and ſome few briefe obſeruations. Which collection I haue the rather made, for that the things contained in this Memoriall, that are of leaſt importance and doubtful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, being drawne from Records and Relations of honorable and credible perſons, the contents thereof which are of greateſt unportance, and may ſeeme moſt doubtfull, are teſtified and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerred by theſe paſſages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The charge which he had of a Company of men of Armes, is thus recorded by</hi> Malingre <hi>a</hi> French <hi>Hiſtoriographer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> the ſeuenth,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Chronol.</note> who did firſt inſtitute the ordinary Companies of men of Armes in <hi>France,</hi> crected the Company of <hi>Scottiſhmen</hi> of Armes of the remnant of the <hi>Scottiſhmen</hi> ouer-throwne at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ernueil,</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of an hundred men of Armes, and two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Archers, giuing them the firſt place among the
<pb facs="tcp:11020:18"/>
               <hi>French</hi> bands of that kinde: Of which Company the ſaid Author ſaith, that <hi>Bernard Stuart</hi> Lord <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> was the ſecond Captaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his Embaſſage to the King of</hi> Scotland,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Scot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Leſley <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Roſſe <hi>maketh mention in this manner: Charles</hi> the eighth ſent into <hi>Scotland Bernard Stuart</hi> Lord <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> and Doctor <hi>Mallart</hi> his Embaſſadours, to renue the ancient League betweene the two Kings and Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his comming to</hi> England <hi>with King</hi> Henry <hi>the ſeuenth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>the ſaid</hi> Leſley <hi>writeth thus:</hi> He commanded thoſe Forces, that accompanied the Earle of <hi>Richmond</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and did him good ſeruice againſt the Vſurper, King <hi>Richard.</hi> So as the ſaid Earle being crowned King, did therefore e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after fauour the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame is confirmed by the foreſaid</hi> Malingre,<note place="margin">Hiſt. Chronol.</note> 
               <hi>who affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth,</hi> That he was the Kings Lieutenant generall of the Army, which was ſent to <hi>England,</hi> to aſſiſt <hi>Henry</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, againſt <hi>Richard</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of his Embaſſage to the Pope,</hi> Guicciardin <hi>writeth thus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his Hiſt. of Italy. l. 1.</note> King <hi>Charles</hi> ſent to the Pope foure Embaſſadours: to wit, <hi>Bernard D'Aubigni</hi> a Chiefetaine, being a <hi>Scottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> by Nation, one of the Treaſurers of <hi>France,</hi> the Preſident of the Parliament of <hi>Proumce,</hi> and <hi>Peron de Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where is to be noted, that among men of ſuch dignity he had the firſt place. Yea, he was of ſuch reputation, as</hi> Paulus Iouius <hi>doth name no other Embaſſador but him, writing of his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage in this wiſe:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Pope was ſent for Embaſſador,<note place="margin">Hiſt. l. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard D'Aubig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> a Scottiſhman, of the Royall Family of the <hi>Stuarts,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed Warriour: who had direction in his iourney to <hi>Rome</hi> to treat with <hi>Iohn Bentiuoli, then Lord of Bononia,</hi> Hercules D'Eſte, <hi>Duke of</hi> Ferrara, Peter de Medices, <hi>Chiefe Commander of the Common wealth of</hi> Florence, and Pandulpho Petrucci <hi>of</hi> Siena: As alſo comming to thoſe Cities to learne what power they had, and how they were
<pb facs="tcp:11020:19"/>pitulation of <hi>Atella,</hi> (<hi>whereby the</hi> Frenchmen, <hi>after a great ouer-throw, the Duke of</hi> Monpenſier <hi>being their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, were bound to depart out of the Kingdome of</hi> Naples) <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaluo</hi> returned into <hi>Calabria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Hiſp. 126. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the greateſt part whereof was in his abſence brought vnder the <hi>French</hi> yoke by <hi>D'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigni</hi> a moſt valiant and ſtirring warriour, but a man of valour and wiſedome more approued, then fortunate, for that he had to deale with ſo ſtrong an Aduerſary: whoſe diligence preſſing him euery where, he was conſtrained to yeeld to the Articles of agreement made with common conſent by the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> and leauing <hi>Italy,</hi> to returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the enterpriſe of</hi> Milllain,<note place="margin">Auregne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Louis 12.</note> Du Haillan <hi>hath theſe paſſages that follow:</hi> The King had aſſembled an Army of fiue and twenty thouſand footemen, and of ſixe thouſand horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. He gaue the conduct of them to <hi>Bernard Stuart,</hi> Lord <hi>D'Aubigni, Lewis</hi> of <hi>Luxenbourg,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ligni,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Giacomo Triuulcio;</hi> all men of great experience and ſufficiency in the Myſtery of Armes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> aſſaulting <hi>Nona</hi> with his troupes, tooke it at the firſt aſſault. The City of <hi>Dertona</hi> was yeelded immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately after to him.</p>
            <p>And they of <hi>Pauia</hi> fearing the mis-fortune of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrians,</hi> did not make longer reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>Paulus Iouius <hi>naming D'Aubigni the principall Leader in this enterpriſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. epit. l 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſaith,</hi> That <hi>Sforza</hi> being aſtoniſhed by the newes which he had of the defeate of his Army, and of the taking of <hi>Alexandrta,</hi> was quite diſ-heartned: and lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Milain,</hi> fled to the Emperour <hi>Maximilian:</hi> and that ſoone after, King <hi>Lewis</hi> hauing receiued the moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing newes of this victory, came to <hi>Milain;</hi> and that all the Townes of <hi>Sforza's</hi> dominion, with the City of <hi>Genua,</hi> yeelded to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the enterpriſe of</hi> Naples, Du Haillan <hi>hath written that which followeth in ſundry places:</hi> D'Aubigni departed from Milain <hi>with twenty thouſand footemen, and foure thouſand
<pb facs="tcp:11020:19"/>Horſemen.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au. Regnt de Louis 12.</note> 
               <hi>He tooke the Caſtles of the Lords of the houſe of Columna well fortified, ſome by force, and ſome by compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When hee came to paſſe the Riuer of Gariglian, the Frenchmen were moleſted by the Enemies Army. But the Lord <hi>D'Aubignt</hi> lowdly reproching to the French Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men their arrogant boaſting a little before, that they alone without the helpe of the Foot-men, would ouercome their enemies, they ſet on them ſo couragiouſly, as at the firſt encounter they put them to flight.</p>
            <p>Soone after Naples yeelded, and King <hi>Frederic</hi> did capitulate with the Lord <hi>D'Aubigni,</hi> that the King ſhuld giue him a certaine yeerely Penſion. He had leaue alſo to carry away his moueables, and contented himſelfe with the Lord <hi>D'Aubigni's</hi> Letters to the King, and without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other aſſurance, came into France to the King, who gratified him not onely with the penſion promiſed to him, but alſo gaue him many good townes, houſes, and faire gardens.</p>
            <p>The affaires of Naples being ended, the King was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with no other care, but of ſettling the ſtate thereof, which (as it happeneth in time of war) was very much ſhaken. To which end hee commanded fiue Ciuilians, of honeſt life, and good reputation, to bee admitted into the Senate. And ſome telling the Lord <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> of the learning of <hi>Iouianus Pontanus,</hi> he fell into ſuch a liking of him, as ſending for him, the next day he beſtowed on him great and rich Preſents, and offered him a place in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, with the fiue already choſen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hitherto</hi> Du Haillan <hi>maketh no mention of the Duke of Nemours, but aſcribes to the Lord</hi> D'Aubigni <hi>what ſoeuer was done, eyther in warre, or in ſettling the State. But hee ſaith,</hi> That after, the King gaue the chiefe authority to <hi>Lewis</hi> of Armaignac, Duke of Nemours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As for the diſcord, which fell betweene the</hi> Frenchmen <hi>and</hi> Spaniards, <hi>for the confines of that Kingdome diuided betweene
<pb facs="tcp:11020:20"/>both their Kings,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Hiſp. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Marian <hi>ſaith,</hi> That after the taking of Naples, there aroſe diſcord betwixt both Nations, as it muſt needs haue come to paſſe, they being in conditions, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and faſhions extremely different.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Of the Lord</hi> D'Aubignies <hi>iourney into Calabria, going to warre againſt the Spaniards,</hi> Iouius <hi>writeth in this manner: D'Aubigni,</hi> who had next to the Duke of Nemours the greateſt authority in the Army, went to Calabria with the third part thereof, being there much renowmed, both for hauing in the time of King <hi>Charles</hi> with great moderation and mildneſſe gouerned that Nation Demi-Grecian, and for that by his Martiall proweſſe he ouercame King <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand,</hi> and <hi>Conſaluo</hi> in a memorable battell: So as in all mens iudgement he was preferred before all other French Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders. For which reſpects, there were many beholding and well-affected to him in particular, beſides them which were of the Angeuine faction. The principall of thoſe were the Princes of Biſignan, and Salerne, and the Earle of Mileto, who reuolted from the Spaniards, as ſoone as the two Kings fell at variance. The Lord <hi>D'Aubignies</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was much deſired by them, deſiring as much to help him in the War with their ſeruice and meanes, which were more then meane. They, together with others of the ſame part, inuited him by letters and meſſages to haſten his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and to ſhew the Banners of France to that people, ready to follow them. Wherefore, ſatiſfying their deſire, as ſoone as he came, he found himſelfe not deceiued in the expectation which he had of their affection &amp; ſeruice. For both in Coſenza their chiefe City, and in all the other Townes of that Prouince, the gates were opened to him, and the Spaniſh Garriſons &amp; Officers driuen out of them; ſo as with very little bloud-ſhed he wanneall the Country, euen to the very ſtraits of Meſſina.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The battell of Terine, and his victory is ſet forth by the ſaid Iouius. Don Hugo de Cardona,</hi> with an Army which hee brought from Sicilie, hauing much annoyed the French
<pb facs="tcp:11020:20"/>party in Calabria: the Lord <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> went to encounter him, hauing in his Army the Princes of Beſignan and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerne with their troupes, <hi>Grigni</hi> with his light Horſe-men, and <hi>Malherbe</hi> with his Gaſcoyne Archers, and three Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of Heluetians. But his principall ſtrength conſiſted in his men of Armes, among which was moſt eminent a wing of Scottiſh-men, which were his familiars, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to him. The enemies informed of his preparation, did not expect him til two dayes after they had notice thereof. But this expert and vigilant Captaine beguil'd their expec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For with French expedition marching night and day, through wayes little hanted, hee ſhewed himſelfe to them the next morning, and forth with ſet on them. The Spaniards ſuſtained couragioully the aſſault, ſo as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat was alike fierce and bloudy on both ſides. <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> ſeeing this, commanded <hi>Grigni</hi> with his wing to ruſh vpon the Spaniſh and Sicilian Infantery; which hee doing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered them. On the other ſide, the Enemies Horſemen, by the encouragement &amp; example of <hi>Cardona,</hi> ſuſtained the aſſault of the Calabrians, with like ſlaughter on both parts. But <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> aduancing his troups, the Spaniſh and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilian Cauallery not being able to reſiſt the Scottiſh-men of Armes, was defeated, and therewithall the Infantery was ouerthrowne &amp; cut in pieces. <hi>Grigni</hi> a moſt valiant Knight was ſlaine in the combat, and <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> himſelfe being in like danger, was reſcued by meanes of <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of Alba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, calling others to ſuccor him, as <hi>Du Haillan</hi> teſtifieth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As concerning the ouerthrow which hee had not long after this victory,</hi> Du Haillan <hi>relateth it to this purpoſe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Au Regne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Lours 12.</note> 
               <hi>Don Hugo de Cardona,</hi> hauing repaired his Army, increaſed the ſame with a new ſupply of fiue thouſand, ſo that his Army con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of eight thouſand men in Armes. And albeit the Lord <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> knew the aduantage they had in number, neuertheleſſe, being confident in his owne ſufficiency, and the tried valour of his Souldiers, and weary of waiting for new ſupply from the King, he reſolued to try the fortune
<pb facs="tcp:11020:21"/>of warre.<note place="margin">In vit. Conſ. l. 2</note> But his Army was defeated, and he himſelfe being in danger to be ſlaine, was reſcued by a troupe of Scottiſhmen, <hi>whoſe valour in this fight</hi> Iouius <hi>commendeth, as alſo he telleth how</hi> D'Aubigni <hi>was reſcued by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In naming the Generall of the</hi> Spaniards <hi>in this battell,</hi> Mariana <hi>and</hi> Iouius <hi>differ from</hi> Du Haillan: <hi>for they call the Generall</hi> Ferdinand Andrada.</p>
            <p>Guicciardin <hi>maketh mention of his defeate in theſe words: D'Aubigni</hi> was defeated and taken in the ſame place,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> wherein ſome yeeres before, hee had with ſo much glory ouercome and diſcomfited King <hi>Ferdmand</hi> and <hi>Conſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo:</hi> So vnconſtant is the proſperity of Fortune. He was one of the moſt excellent Captaines that <hi>Charles</hi> brought into <hi>Italy,</hi> and of a free and noble diſpoſition. And this his miſ-fortune proceeded only from a too earneſt deſire of victory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This teſtimony of</hi> Guicciardin, <hi>(who is held to be ſparing, yea, niggardly in commending any man) eſpecially being giuen in the time of his miſ-fortune, maketh much for his bonour. But the too great earneſtneſſe whereof he ſeemeth to taxe him, is by</hi> Mariana <hi>(though otherwiſe as tarte in cenſuring as he is) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted warlike policy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Hiſp. l. 27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>howbeit wanting ſucceſſe: for he telleth,</hi> That by the death of <hi>Porto Carrero</hi> Generall of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, chancing at that time, there ariſing a ielouſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the chiefe of the Army about the ſucceeding to him, and the Souldiers being diſcontented for want of pay, <hi>D'Aubignt</hi> hauing intelligence thereof, and hoping thereby to winne aduantage, did then offer them battell, albeit he failed in the ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is likewiſe probable, that hee was rather moued to fight, ſeeing the decay of the</hi> Frenchmen, <hi>and the</hi> Spaniards <hi>preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, as alſo the Kings ſlackneſſe in ſending thither ſupply of men or money,</hi> the ſaid King being (as Du Haillan ſaith) ſo niggardly and pinching, that it is the common opinion, that fearing he ſhould ſpend mony in vaine, he ſuffred the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Dutchy of <hi>Milain</hi> to be loſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Iouius</hi> ſaith, That after this ouerthrow,<note place="margin">In vit. Conſ. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>D'Aubigni</hi> with drew himſelfe into the Fortreſſe of <hi>Angitola,</hi> complaining of Fortune, which had ſo deceiued him, hauing beene til then inuincible, &amp; twelue times been victorious in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, ſince he began to be a Warriour in <hi>France</hi> &amp; <hi>Britaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whence wee may gather, that many of his military actions and victories are wrapped in obliuion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſame</hi> Iouius <hi>telleth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vit. Conſ. l. 2</note> That whiles hee was beſieged in the ſaid fortreſſe, the Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> hauing beene ſlaine, and his Army defeated by the <hi>Spantards</hi> at <hi>Cirig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nola,</hi> and <hi>Conſaluo's</hi> letters touching this victory, hauing beene ſent to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Commanders that beſieged him, and by them to him, he ſaid, that he perceiued Fortune to bee very oppoſite to the <hi>French</hi> part; and therefore iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it folly and wilfulneſſe to withſtand her, he promiſed that he would yeeld himſelfe, if that were true, which was written. Whereof being certified by Meſſengers, which he had purpoſely ſent out to know the truth, he came out of the Caſtell apparelled in cloth of <hi>Tiſſue,</hi> and with a cheerefull and merry countenance yeelded himſelfe, vpon condition that all thoſe of his company ſhould be ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and himſelfe only kept in free cuſtody. And it is ſaid, that he ſharply reproued two young Lords, his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, (who were after renowmed Warriours) for that more faintly, then was fit for men, namely, for them being <hi>Scottiſhmen,</hi> and of the Bloud Royall, they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waile the vnfortunate ſucceſſe of the warre, not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, that valiant men ſhould neuer be diſ-heartned, but ſeeke by afreſh endeuour of vertue reuiued and growne inuincible, to recouer Fortunes fauour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A witty conceit of his and</hi> Conſaluo's <hi>returne to him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In vit. Conſ. l. 3</note> 
               <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue made mention, are contained in this relation of the ſame Author:</hi> When the <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> after <hi>Gayeta</hi> was yeelded, were ready to depart from the Kingdome of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Conſaluo</hi> offering horſes to many of them, <hi>D'Aubig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> their Commander ſaid to him, ſmiling: Sir, let vs then<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:22"/>
            <p>THeſe Wiſhes following, directed and preſented to the Prince's Highneſſe at his Creation, I haue put to the preſſe rather now, then heretofore; for that I thought them, being contained in ſo few leaues, leſſe fit to bee publiſhed apart vnder the ſhelter of his Princely Name, then now, when as they adde ſomewhat to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Memoriall dedicated to his Highneſſe. And I haue the rather at this time publiſhed them, how homely &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poliſhed ſoeuer they bee, becauſe I hope that the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe both of their honeſt Subiect, and Princely Obiect will make them not to ſeeme at any time vnſeaſonable.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_prince">
            <head>To the Prince's Highneſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>THee to inſtruct it is not here my drift, (proue,</hi> GREAT PRINCE: <hi>I only wiſh that ſuch thou As Thee to be thy</hi> Royall Fathers <hi>Loue And Wiſedom teacheth in his</hi> ROYALL GIFT.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:22"/>
            <head>WISHES PRESENTED TO THE PRINCE'S Highneſſe at his CREATION.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOW that each loyall heart of kingdomes three</l>
               <l>Doth ioyfully congratulate with thee,</l>
               <l>Moſt worthy Prince, in this thy Honor new,</l>
               <l>Which by thy birth-right doth to thee accrew,</l>
               <l>All wiſhing thee all ioy and happineſſe,</l>
               <l>Their inward ioy all ſtriuing to expreſſe</l>
               <l>With cheerefull countenance and applauding words,</l>
               <l>With Bone-fires, Triumphs, Muſicall accords;</l>
               <l>And ſome with Muſes Panegyricke ſtraines;</l>
               <l>Though I come ſhort of them, whoſe happy veines</l>
               <l>Of Poetry can make thy Fame to flouriſh,</l>
               <l>Yet ſith thy worth and fauour to me nouriſh</l>
               <l>My loue to thee, and cheriſh my deſire</l>
               <l>To honour thee, as fewell doth the fire,</l>
               <l>I muſt at this thy new aduancement vſe,</l>
               <l>To ſhew my ioy, the chaunting of my muſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſith it is too homely to ſet forth</l>
               <l>In any Panegyrike verſe thy worth,</l>
               <l>I leaue the taske of acting ſuch a part</l>
               <l>To them who can it act with better Art,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:23"/>
               <l>That thou maiſt <hi>Iuſtice</hi> doe, and loue it too,</l>
               <l>Since Tyrants for their ends oft <hi>Iuſtice</hi> doe:</l>
               <l>And that thy ſword of <hi>Iuſtice</hi> doe not ſpare</l>
               <l>Such crimes, as haynous and malicious are:</l>
               <l>That thou her Ballance equally doe weigh,</l>
               <l>Not ſuffering ſpleen or fauour it to ſway:</l>
               <l>That men accuſ'd may haue this iuſt refuge,</l>
               <l>That thou wilt heare both parties ere thou iudge:</l>
               <l>That in rewards as well as puniſhment,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Iuſtice</hi> mens deſerts to weigh be bent:</l>
               <l>That it may giue to euery man his owne,</l>
               <l>Nor fauour more the Courtier then the Clowne:</l>
               <l>And that thou ſee they, as thy ſelfe, beiuſt,</l>
               <l>Whom to doe <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> thou ſhalt put in truſt:</l>
               <l>That ſpiders webs they make not Laws betoken,</l>
               <l>Which catching ſmaller flies, by waſps are broken:</l>
               <l>That to their ſutors grieuance and decay,</l>
               <l>They may not fruſtrate <hi>Iuſtice</hi> by delay,</l>
               <l>Nor by renuing Suites, like <hi>Hidra's</hi> heads,</l>
               <l>To cramme the Crue, that writes, reports, and pleades:</l>
               <l>That from pretence of Conſcience and Law,</l>
               <l>Decrees againſt them both they may not draw:</l>
               <l>That th'Vnder-Rulers of thy flocks may feare</l>
               <l>To flea them, or vniuſtly them to ſheare:</l>
               <l>That as the members doe the head defend,</l>
               <l>And it to them doth health and ſafety ſend;</l>
               <l>So may thy ſubiects Thee, thou them protect,</l>
               <l>And may thy <hi>Iuſtice</hi> none of them neglect:</l>
               <l>That, when thou ſhalt thy Royal <hi>Sire</hi> ſucceed,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Iuſtice</hi> may thee loue and glory breed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But for that <hi>Iuſtice</hi> is a kinde of racke,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Mercy</hi> make it not with meaſure ſlacke,</l>
               <l>I wiſh that thou doe <hi>Clemency</hi> imbrace,</l>
               <l>As beſt reſembling God in ſuch a caſe:</l>
               <l>That men to loue thee rather thou allure</l>
               <l>By <hi>Mercy,</hi> then by rigour awe procure:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:23"/>
               <l>That thou ſometime thy <hi>Clemency</hi> extend,</l>
               <l>Where there is hope th'offender will amend;</l>
               <l>And when as thence no publike ſcandall growes,</l>
               <l>Nor wrong to any priuate perſon flowes;</l>
               <l>Or when the fault concernes thee in ſuch wiſe,</l>
               <l>As thence to thee no danger may ariſe:</l>
               <l>That rather in thine owne, then others wrong,</l>
               <l>To true remorſe thy mercy doe belong:</l>
               <l>That wilfull malice with farre greater terror</l>
               <l>Thou puniſh, then weake frailty or blinde error:</l>
               <l>That thou, as aboue ſlanders reach, contemne</l>
               <l>The Sland'rer, making him himſelfe condemne,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Philip, Iulius, Auguſt, Antonine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> did; whoſe glory ſtill doth ſhine:</l>
               <l>That thou delight men to relieue and ſpare;</l>
               <l>But puniſh them with griefe that guilty are;</l>
               <l>Yet temper ſo in Country, Court, and City</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Mercy,</hi> as it proue not fooliſh pity:</l>
               <l>That when thou ſhalt this Vertue put in vre,</l>
               <l>With honor, ſafety it may thee procure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then wiſh I, that, as <hi>Iuſtice</hi> thou ſhalt cheriſh,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Clemency</hi> her ſiſter, ſo thou nouriſh</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> in performing promiſes, the prop</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and of Honors height the top:</l>
               <l>That for a certaine truth thou vnderſtand</l>
               <l>This Vertue rare to be the ſureſt band</l>
               <l>Of friendſhip, commerce and ſociety,</l>
               <l>And trueſt badge of morall honeſty;</l>
               <l>That thou in word and practice it obſerue,</l>
               <l>And neuer from it be induc'd to ſwerue:</l>
               <l>And that not onely for thy wiſhed ends</l>
               <l>Thou keepe thy promiſe, or for loue to friends,</l>
               <l>But alſo to thy foes for Vertues ſake;</l>
               <l>Whereby of foes thy friends thou maiſt them make:</l>
               <l>That thou but for ſome vrgent cauſe bee loth:</l>
               <l>T'ingage thy ſelfe by word, but more by othe:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:24"/>
               <l>But that, when thou ſhalt do it, no reſpect</l>
               <l>Thy plighted faith induce thee to neglect;</l>
               <l>So as thy promiſe iuſt and lawfull be,</l>
               <l>Which euer to be ſuch thou muſt foreſee:</l>
               <l>That thy reſpect of honeſty and fame</l>
               <l>May win thee of a faithfull Prince the name:</l>
               <l>That ſuch perfidious counſell thou deteſt,</l>
               <l>As would remoue this Vertue from thy breſt,</l>
               <l>Since not the purchaſe of a Diadem</l>
               <l>Can counteruaile the loſſe of ſuch a gem.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſince no vertue to a Prince or King</l>
               <l>More loue doth purchaſe then his <hi>Bounty,</hi> ſpring</l>
               <l>And fountaine of his bountifull rewards,</l>
               <l>And Princely gifts; thy honour who regards,</l>
               <l>Cannot but wiſh thee to be liberall,</l>
               <l>And ſo do I: yet wiſh I therewithall,</l>
               <l>That Iudgement may thy Bounty ſo direct,</l>
               <l>As therein be no notable defect,</l>
               <l>Nor great exceſſe; both which extremities</l>
               <l>Are vices that do blinde mens inward eyes,</l>
               <l>And make them without meaſure ſpend or ſpare:</l>
               <l>Wherefore I wiſh that with a heedefull care</l>
               <l>Thou to the golden meane thy ſelfe apply,</l>
               <l>In being frugall, and not niggardly;</l>
               <l>As alſo that thou ſpend with a due meaſure,</l>
               <l>And not exhauſt by lauiſhing thy treaſure:</l>
               <l>That ordring ſo thy Bounty by proportion,</l>
               <l>Thou neuer neede ſupply it with extortion:</l>
               <l>That Thrift thy Bounties treaſurer thou make:</l>
               <l>That men of merit may thereof partake;</l>
               <l>To wit, ſuch as for ſeruice done deſerue,</l>
               <l>Or they who can thee and their country ſerue:</l>
               <l>That thy rewards for ſeruice place may haue</l>
               <l>Before thy gifts, as equity doth craue:</l>
               <l>Yet that thy Bounty alſo thou extend</l>
               <l>To men diſtreſſd, and for thy honor ſpend</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11020:24"/>
               <l>In all occaſions, that may it aduance,</l>
               <l>And namely in the princely maintenance</l>
               <l>Of thine Eſtate and Court in euery thing,</l>
               <l>Which might neglected ſtaine to honour bring:</l>
               <l>And that too much thou do not giue to any,</l>
               <l>That thou thereby mai'ſt giue the more to many:</l>
               <l>That impudence and importunity</l>
               <l>May not extort thy <hi>Liberality:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But that thou freely moſt on them beſtow,</l>
               <l>Who beſt deſerue, although in asking ſlow:</l>
               <l>And that to ſuch as by thy gifts would thriue,</l>
               <l>Much rather, then to Spend-thrifts, thou do giue:</l>
               <l>That, where t'impart thy bounty thou haſt reaſon,</l>
               <l>Thou doe not long delay, but giue in ſeaſon:</l>
               <l>That as by others rather, then by thee,</l>
               <l>That ſhould be done which may diſtaſtfull bee;</l>
               <l>So meerely from thy ſelfe thy Bounty flow,</l>
               <l>That men may thankes to thee, not t'others ow:</l>
               <l>That, as to many thou ſhalt liberall proue,</l>
               <l>So God to thee be in his grace and loue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moreouer, ſith a Prince not only deckt</l>
               <l>Muſt be with vertues, that may him direct</l>
               <l>To rule in peace, but muſt be arm'd likewiſe</l>
               <l>With Fortitude againſt each enterpriſe</l>
               <l>Of Foes, or Rebels, that would make a breach</l>
               <l>Of peace in his eſtate, or yet impeach</l>
               <l>His honour with vnſufferable wrongs,</l>
               <l>This Vertue is my wiſhes eeke belong's,</l>
               <l>Moſt noble Prince, ſince it belongs to thee,</l>
               <l>Their worthy Obiect, whom I wiſh to bee</l>
               <l>A ſecond <hi>Magnus,</hi> or firſt <hi>Maximus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As thou art borne to be firſt <hi>Carolus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of Kingdoms three: which that thou maiſt defend,</l>
               <l>And them repreſſe, that would thy hurt intend,</l>
               <l>I wiſh thou be as ſtout and valiant found,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Charlemaigne</hi> for valour moſt renown'd:</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:25"/>
            <lg>
               <head>A ſon Alteſſe.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>CHarles,</hi> qui fais honneur a ta Principautè,</l>
               <l>Non moins qu'a t'honnorer d'elle ſert la puiſſance,</l>
               <l>Maintenant qu' inueſti tu yes, par naiſſance</l>
               <l>'Digne heritier estant d'une haute Royautè;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pour tes faueurs &amp; dons, amour &amp; Loyautè</l>
               <l>Te debuant, ce beau iour, qui d'honneur accroiſſance</l>
               <l>Te donne, ie celebre auec reiouiſſance,</l>
               <l>Et te rens par ma <hi>Muſe</hi> humble hommage &amp; feautè.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ce que dignement faire en <hi>Hymnes</hi> ou <hi>Cantiques</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ne ponuant par ſes vers, &amp; chanſons trop Ruſtiques,</l>
               <l>D' elle aidè ie le fai par mes <hi>Voeus</hi> &amp; <hi>Souhaits;</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Priant, qu'apres ton Pere en la <hi>Grande Bretagne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tu regnes longuement vn autre <hi>Charlemagne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Grand en merite, &amp; gloire, &amp; plein d'heur a iamais.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Ad eundem Illuſtriſsimum Principem.</head>
               <l>NOn tibi delato, <hi>Princeps,</hi> tam laetor honore,</l>
               <l>Quàm magis excelſum quòd mereare decus.</l>
               <l>Nam gener is qui iure tui, ceu more vetuſto,</l>
               <l>I am tibi conting it, ſit lices amplus hones;</l>
               <l>Maiori tamen eſſe parem te, quae indolis altae</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtutis <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tuae das, document a docent:</l>
               <l>Quae precor augeſcant, poſsis vt ſemper honores</l>
               <l>Creſcentes meritis anteuenire tuis.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11020:25"/>
            <head>In nomen Illuſtriſsimi Principis: <hi>Carolus Princeps Walliae</hi> Anagramma: <hi>Clarus in pace, praelio, luſu.</hi> Acroſtichis vtrum que continens.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>CArolus incedit tam re, quàm nomine <seg rend="rightJustify">Clarus,</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Auctus honore noue, defert quem pectore <seg rend="rightJustify">Laeto</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Rex illi genitor que; vnde vrbs laetatur, &amp; <seg rend="rightJustify">Aula,</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Omnis eitriplicis gratatur &amp; Incola <seg rend="rightJustify">Regni.</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Laeto hine applauſu quiſque, &amp; modulamine <seg rend="rightJustify">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocis,</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Vultu hilari, &amp; cunctis animo quae gaudia <seg rend="rightJustify">Sentit</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Significare modis geſtit: ſibi debita <seg rend="rightJustify">Iure</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Princeps eximia quae ſint facit indole <seg rend="rightJustify">Noſter.</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Regem ſpondet eum namque haec fore tempore <seg rend="rightJustify">Pacis</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Inſtitia, Pietate, fide, tum <hi>Palladis</hi> 
                  <seg rend="rightJustify">Arte,</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Necnon magnanimo, ſed miti, pectore <seg rend="rightJustify">Clarum;</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Commoda curantem populorum, his ceu pater <seg rend="rightJustify">Eſſet;</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Egregium belleque Ducem, cuirobore <seg rend="rightJustify">Pectus</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Polleat inuicto, geſtarum Encomia <seg rend="rightJustify">Rerum</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Sint cui grande decus parituraque nomen in <seg rend="rightJustify">Aeuum,</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Virtutis ſpecimen cum claſse per aequora <seg rend="rightJustify">Latè</seg>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor praebuerit, terraque hoſtilibus <seg rend="rightJustify">Inſtans</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Armatus cuneis hoſtes ſuperauerit <seg rend="rightJustify">Omnes.</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Laudem hancipſe tuus praeſagit, Carole, <seg rend="rightJustify">Luſus:</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Ludis Eques tu, ſiue Pedes, tuae viuida <seg rend="rightJustify">Virtus</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Inde futura patet: ſucceſſu haec Numina <seg rend="rightJustify">Summa</seg>
               </l>
               <l>Aetheris eſſe meis dent Omina conſona <seg rend="rightJustify">Votis.</seg>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
